<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spirit of prelacie, yet working. Or, Truth from under a cloud, in a relation, of that great, and publike contestation had in Glocester, July, 1644. Written then, and now published, as it were of necessity. Together, with a postscript, containing some generall and perticular observations, upon Master Edwards his Gangræna. / By Robert Bacon, M.A. minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Bacon, Robert, M.A.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E334_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9476</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873552</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873552</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159660</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77072)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159660)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 54:E334[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spirit of prelacie, yet working. Or, Truth from under a cloud, in a relation, of that great, and publike contestation had in Glocester, July, 1644. Written then, and now published, as it were of necessity. Together, with a postscript, containing some generall and perticular observations, upon Master Edwards his Gangræna. / By Robert Bacon, M.A. minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Bacon, Robert, M.A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.L. for Giles Calvert, at the black-spread-eagle at the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On the action by the city of Gloucester in suppressing Bacon's preaching and expelling him from the city.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary order to print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Edwards, Thomas, 1599-1647. --  Gangraena --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Preaching --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Gloucester (England) --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159660:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SPIRIT <hi>OF</hi> PRELACIE, YET WORKING.</p>
            <p>OR, <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH from under a CLO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>D,</hi> IN A RELATION, of that <hi>Great,</hi> and <hi>Publike</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation had in <hi>Gloceſter, July,</hi> 1644.</p>
            <p>Written then, and now publiſhed, as it were of neceſſity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TOGETHER,</hi> With a POSTSCRIPT, containing ſome <hi>generall</hi> and <hi>perticular</hi> Obſervations, upon Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> his <hi>Gangraena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By ROBERT BACON, M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 97.5.</bibl> The hils melted <hi>like wax at the</hi> preſence of the Lord.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 11.19.</bibl> 
               <hi>Wiſdom is iuſtified of her</hi> children.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Tertul. Apol. contr. Gent. Cap. 3.</bibl> 
               <hi>Bonus vir,</hi> Cajus Sejus, <hi>malus tantum</hi> quod Chriſtianus.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. L.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the black-ſpread-eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:159660:2"/>
            <p>THis <hi>remarkable</hi> Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, penned with a <hi>ſweet ſpirit</hi> of <hi>meekneſſe,</hi> one of the moſt <hi>Sovereigne remedies</hi> for all our diviſions, in my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſerves to be Printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Aprill</hi> 11. 1646.</date>
               <signed>John Bachiler.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:159660:2"/>
            <head>An intimation to the READER</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Worlds <hi>full of Controverſie</hi> already, and <hi>ſo full,</hi> that the truth is wofully <hi>obſcured,</hi> and <hi>obſtructed by them,</hi> otherwiſe this <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> might have ſwoln into a greater <hi>Volume,</hi> but there is <hi>no end of diſputes,</hi> Solomons adviſe is good, <hi>the beginning of ſtrife is,</hi> as when one letteth <hi>out water,</hi> therefore leave off contention before it <hi>be medled with,</hi> wherefore here is only a <hi>Narrative</hi> of what was done in the <hi>face of</hi> that whole <hi>City,</hi> and is left upon <hi>Record,</hi> not only in the <hi>mindes</hi> and memories of them that were <hi>ſpectators,</hi> but alſo <hi>doubles</hi> in the books of <hi>Record,</hi> in the hands of thoſe <hi>in Authoritie</hi> in that place, there being nothing <hi>done</hi> but in <hi>their eye,</hi> and by <hi>their Order,</hi> therefore no <hi>offence</hi> can be given by the repetition of <hi>the Names of any,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but the <hi>ſubſcription</hi> of their <hi>own hands,</hi> which every one cannot chuſe <hi>but owne,</hi> all perticulars <hi>in the Diſpute</hi> cannot be <hi>reported,</hi> but the generall <hi>carriage</hi> of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is <hi>faithfully related</hi> from the <hi>beginning</hi> to the end, the <hi>objection</hi> againſt the <hi>Printing</hi> of this Relation muſt be this, <hi>to what end?</hi> the thing it ſelfe will <hi>anſwer,</hi> it ſerves to a <hi>twofold end, 1</hi> to cleere the <hi>innocent,</hi> then the which nothing is more <hi>needfull in the land, 2</hi> to given <hi>an experiment</hi> of the <hi>ſeaſonableneſſe</hi> of Maſter <hi>Colemans</hi> Caution to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that the <hi>Clergie (ut vocant)</hi> may not carry on their own <hi>ſelf-deſignes,</hi> as here they did, by the ſtrength of <hi>humane power,</hi> a <hi>burthen</hi> under which well-nigh all <hi>Europe,</hi> yea, all the <hi>World groans:</hi> a Reply
<pb facs="tcp:159660:3"/>to the <hi>Queſtions,</hi> here ſtated, long ſince given in, together with a <hi>Rejoynder</hi> made thereto then, is of purpoſe <hi>omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> becauſe I think all men may <hi>now ſee,</hi> its high-time to apply our ſelves <hi>to plant truth in the hearts of thoſe</hi> that know it not, rather then <hi>darken it</hi> by <hi>bitterneſſe</hi> and wrath which fall out <hi>uſually</hi> in diſputes, even among <hi>thoſe</hi> that pretend to <hi>know it,</hi> for whiles men thus <hi>contend</hi> about it, <hi>experience</hi> ſhews many <hi>loſe it,</hi> and themſelves <hi>with it:</hi> the <hi>Weſtern parts</hi> did not more <hi>groan</hi> under the late remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>illegall power there,</hi> then they doe yet under the <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of darkneſſe,</hi> which <hi>prevailing,</hi> keeps them in <hi>a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer,</hi> and a more <hi>diſmall bondage,</hi> yet ſcarce any eye <hi>pitties them,</hi> to <hi>proclaime</hi> the acceptable <hi>yeere of the Lord</hi> unto them: Every man ſuſpects <hi>his brother,</hi> that through the <hi>contention</hi> of the Labourers, the <hi>Vineyards</hi> neglected, the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> darkned, Satan's <hi>advantaged,</hi> and the Saints <hi>burthened,</hi> and <hi>the Name of God blaſphemed,</hi> for if in this we <hi>agree not,</hi> what do we more <hi>then they</hi> that began to <hi>build (a Babel)</hi> which ſtuck in <hi>their hands,</hi> for by this <hi>confuſion</hi> of language, each man is <hi>hindred by</hi> his brother, Wherefore let the Apoſtles be received <hi>among us,</hi> follow peace <hi>with all men, (eſpecially with them that doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve)</hi> and holineſſe, without which no man <hi>ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> that we may <hi>further</hi> one another in that wherein <hi>wee doe agree,</hi> and beare <hi>one</hi> with <hi>another</hi> as becommeth <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> in the things <hi>wherein we differ,</hi> that wee may be a <hi>joy</hi> and not a <hi>vexation</hi> each to other: ſo prays he, <hi>for the brethren,</hi> that is himſelfe a <hi>brother</hi> in the Lord Jeſus.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:159660:3"/>
            <head>To the Right HONOURABLE, WILLIAM, Lord Viſcount, SAY, and SEAL:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have always ſince I ſaw <hi>your perſon,</hi> accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelfe exceedingly below your taking <hi>notice of me,</hi> &amp; ſhould now have thought it as great <hi>preſumption,</hi> to prefix your name to any thing of mine, eſpecially ſuch <hi>a thing as this,</hi> had I not in a ſort been <hi>compeld thereto,</hi> and that not out of any reſpect <hi>to my ſelf,</hi> as having <hi>learned,</hi> being of a long time <hi>accuſtomed</hi> to ſuffer reproch: but becauſe I have bin <hi>ſo frequently</hi> an eare, and now in Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> book, an eye witneſſe, what is <hi>in the dark,</hi> and as it were <hi>at a diſtance,</hi> whiſper'd, by them that <hi>now dare not,</hi> as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>draw too nigh,</hi> as having once or twice <hi>experience,</hi> that their diſapointment in offering <hi>perſonall injuries,</hi> hath not only been an addition <hi>of honour to you,</hi> (which as the Sun appears <hi>brighter after a cloud,</hi>) but have made themſelves <hi>publike examples,</hi> as well of <hi>ignorance,</hi> as <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> and given men to ſee them ſuch <hi>as were foretold</hi> ſhould be in the <hi>the laſt times,</hi> even ſuch as
<note n="a" place="margin">Revel. 22.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>love</hi> and <hi>faſhion</hi> a lye <hi>for advantage,</hi> therefore now like <hi>the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> (that wounds the <hi>womans ſeed in the heel,</hi> becauſe he can do no <hi>further miſchief,</hi>) they <hi>remotely, ſeek,</hi> but
<pb facs="tcp:159660:4"/>in vain, to blemiſh <hi>your honour</hi> for <hi>entertaining</hi> me, who in this <hi>turn of time,</hi> like a veſſell of <hi>ſmall quantity,</hi> have had ſome <hi>dependance</hi> on you, whom God as the glory of your <hi>fathers houſe,</hi> for the ſafety and honour <hi>of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> hath made to <hi>many,</hi> beſides, like <hi>Eliakim,</hi> a <hi>Nail, faſtned</hi> in a ſure place: and thus they direct their arrows, even <hi>bitter words:</hi> I am charg'd afreſh with <hi>errour,</hi> though ſolemnly <hi>diſcharged,</hi> where I was firſt <hi>accuſed,</hi> And this hinted, as <hi>patroniz'd by you,</hi> in entertaining <hi>me,</hi> But the whole <hi>Kingdome</hi> knows, and all the <hi>World may,</hi> That Errours <hi>of all ſorts,</hi> whether <hi>Politicall, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall,</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> have been <hi>eminently,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>emenency</hi> of your honour, and <hi>deep under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> as heretofore, ſo to <hi>this preſent houre, mightily</hi> and <hi>ſucceſsfully,</hi> to the Kingdoms joy, <hi>withſtood by you.</hi> Wherefore, the <hi>humble requeſt</hi> I make to your Honour is, that as opportunity may be given, both <hi>by your ſelfe,</hi> and others, by <hi>your advice,</hi> enquiry may be <hi>made,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe things <hi>be ſo or no,</hi> that God may be <hi>magnified,</hi> the truth <hi>juſtified,</hi> errour <hi>ſilenced,</hi> your honour in that act of entertaining me, <hi>preſerved,</hi> my ſelf alone <hi>aſhamed,</hi> if any ſuch thing be proved <hi>againſt him,</hi> that is willing to offer himſelf to the triall of all, <hi>that love our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> and that the rather, becauſe I have bin <hi>awhile,</hi> more <hi>perticularly:</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours ſervant (according to his meaſure) in the Goſpel of God and our Saviour Jeſus, <hi>ROBERT BACON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159660:4"/>
            <head>A brief Relation of my uſage in <hi>GLOCESTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here being an offence taken (none as I know given) by a Sermon I preached on the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Faſt day,
<note place="margin">As M. <hi>Holford</hi> reported.</note> the Major of the City was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited by Maſter <hi>Marſhall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">By the Majors own report.</note> a man living and preaching among the Cavaliers (as they call them) and one that never heard me ſpeak, or ever, I think with knowledge, ſaw my face, as alſo by M. <hi>Holford</hi> and M. <hi>Corbet</hi> living in Town, that I might preach no more in thoſe parts, ſo that by the Majors ſole authority I was ſilenced for one Lords day, though M. <hi>Holford</hi> confeſſed he durſt not gainſay the Doctrine, onely he ſaid that the Major was greatly diſpleaſed with him for giving me leave, but the Major himſelfe to me affirmed the contrary, namely, that M. <hi>Holford</hi> did moſt earneſtly ſolicite him to manifeſt his power in hindering me from preaching, though I was thereunto called, as by others ſo eſpecially by M. <hi>Hart,</hi> to ſupply his publike Lecture, during the intervall of his journey to <hi>London:</hi> thus M. <hi>Holford</hi> labouring to keep in with both ſides by concealing himſelfe, loſt moſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly the eſteeme, which he expected to have, from both.</p>
            <p>This reſtraint of the Major was taken off again, by the ſole au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Governour Collonel <hi>Maſſie,</hi> being moved thereunto by a Letter I made bold to write to him upon that occaſion, ſo that I preached publikely again every Lords day, for the moſt part twice, and on the Faſt dayes, labouring to cleere out of <hi>Luke</hi> 13.5. the Doctrine of repentance, about which the exception was.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159660:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Hereupon one <hi>Wheeler,</hi> ſomtimes M. <hi>Dorneys</hi> Clerke, and then an under Commiſſary (if I miſtake not) in Sir <hi>William Wallers</hi> Armie, told his acquaintance he would apply himſelfe to take an effectuall courle to remove me out of that City, and therefore addreſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, not onely to take notes of my Sermon, but alſo of my Prayer, thereby to ſtir up adverſaries by giving in information againſt me, which M. <hi>Corbet,</hi> M. <hi>Holford,</hi> and M. <hi>Hodges,</hi> all then in the City, with all readineſſe received: Therefore being confident of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours eare, being nigh unto him, they afterwards made uſe of his authority, to ſummon me by a ſouldier, as a tranſgreſſor, to the Governours Chamber, on the Lords day after evening Sermon, I hearing nothing of it before, where being preſent, the Governour and divers Souldiers, ſome of the Committee, &amp; many of the chief of the City, with I think, all the Miniſters: The Governour with much courteſie and clemencie, told me, he had ſent for me to ſpeak with me, together with the Miniſters, for as much (as he ſaid) he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived many great complaints from them againſt me, that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came in my Miniſtry a very great burthen unto them, but he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped there was no ſuch cauſe given, as was reported, to whom I replyed, what I taught was publique, and if I failed in ought, when it ſhould be made to appear, I ſhould as publikely diſclaim, though my ayme was, as God is witneſſe, the increaſe of knowledge, unity and love, which is much wanting every where, but before I had yet done ſpeaking, the Miniſters upbraided me with much unbeſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and reproachfull language, not giving leave one to another, but ruſhing upon me with a torrent of evill words, till that unſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe was remedied by the Governours Command: Then M. <hi>Holford</hi> began an invective againſt the Hereticks and Schiſmaticks of old, backing his ſpeech with the authority of <hi>Auſtin</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> but being required to make application of his diſcourſe in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular charge aginſt me, he openly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſt in the audience of all that he had nothing to accuſe me of, onely he had me in ſuſpition for this onely reaſon, becauſe the people had ſuch recourſe unto me and their congregations where he &amp; the reſt of the Miniſters taught though heretofore they were like to <hi>Pharoahs</hi> fat kine (which was a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude hee uſed) yet others like the lean kine had even eaten them up:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159660:5"/>But having nothing actually to accuſe me of, &amp; having (as it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent) before hand laid their heads together, and determined among themſelves to examine me upon certain intergatories, that they might have wherewithall, if poſſible, from mine own mouth, to lay to my charge, &amp; they did as they, thought, but this unchriſtian and un-miniſterlike courſe of theirs, Iutterly diſclaimed for the preſent, as not being bound to accuſe my ſelfe; they induſtriouſly ſeeking and not finding matter ſufficient for an accuſation againſt me, and becauſe too it ſavoured ſo ſtrongly of the illegality of the High-Commiſſion-Court, againſt which all men did of late moſt juſtly complain, yet at length they prevailed with me, caſting upon me much reproach,
<note place="margin">Though he was a conſtant hearer of mee.</note> and labouring with many words to bring me into contempt, and M. <hi>Shepheard</hi> of the Committee began to urge that he now did ſuſpect my Doctrine was not ſound, becauſe I did refuſe to confeſſe it, eſpecially ſaid M. <hi>Corbet</hi> and M. <hi>Hodges,</hi> being convented before the Magiſtrate (though indeed by the Miniſters undue inſtigation thereunto) to that very end as they ſaid, till by their importunity I was even aſhamed to be any longer ſilent: whereupon I anſwered to ten Queſtions which M. <hi>Holford,</hi> M. <hi>Corbet,</hi> and M. <hi>Hodges</hi> in their wiſdoms thought meet, in writing to propound unto me, whereunto I ſubſcribed either affirmatively or negatively as I thought meet, and as the Lord then gave me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, but upon this condition onely, that I might have time, which was given me till Wedneſday morning by the Governour to ſtate the queſtions, as I conceived them, when the time came, (for as for that night I was very courteouſly entertained at the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours Table.) I had the word of command from Colonel <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> then Governour, by a Souldier ſent to that purpoſe to repair immediately to his Chamber, where after a little ſtay, I went in the company, and by the direction of M. <hi>Holford</hi> and M. <hi>Hodges,</hi> to the place where the Councell of War was wont to be kept, whether there came after wards the Governour, and many Commanders and Souldiers, the whole Committee that were then in Town, the Major, and other chiefe men of the City, with divers Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and very many Miniſters and others, and they that could not get into the room (it being an under chamber) they ſtood
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159660:6"/>without at a broad window that gave light into it, where they both heard and ſaw what was done in it. Every one being ſetled in his place, I according to a formercommand, gave into the hands of the Governour in writing an Anſwer to thoſe ten Queſtions; which by the Miniſters were propounded to me the Lords day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: This by the Governours command was then put into the hands of M. <hi>Corbet</hi> (who it ſeems was intended to diſpute with me about them) to read which he began in the audience of the people, but gave off in the midſt, as being unwilling that the company ſhould heare altogether, and therefore would diſpute with me im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before he read, them all, which I utterly refuſed, becauſe I was not ordered then to diſpute, but to give in my Anſwer to the Queſtions in writing, which anſwer was but ſhort, and might have been quick diſpatcht: Some reaſoning yet there was among us about the Queſtions, but with the greateſt confuſion that might be, there being ſomtimes three, and ſometimes foure, and ſomtimes more, ſpeaking unto me at the ſame time, and challenging me to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, many uſing reproachfull language (eſpecially young M. <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>) againſt me, &amp; ſome blows threatned me, which had I not been a Miniſter (as they ſaid) I ſhould have felt, but the company aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to heare ſuch language from one in authority, they ſalved it up with this excuſe, that if I had been a Souldier I ſhould have had the cenſure of an offending Souldier: Another of no mean com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand (fiery indeed in zeale, but without knowledge) haling me with violence by the arme, ſaid the devill was in me, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards openly profeſt by his conſent, I ſhould be rewarded with fire and faggot, for which cauſe the people called him <hi>Bonner,</hi> as himſelfe acknowledged in my hearing in the Committee Room, beſides divers of the Miniſters, once a Cavalier, taken in Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliamen, ſeen reel in the ſtreets through drunkenneſſe, having now his freedom, openly jeering me, the like I confeſſe I never met with, but from Biſhop <hi>Skinner</hi> of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> of whom I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered very much.</p>
            <p>In concluſion, a writing was drawn up by conſent among them to this effect (a Copy whereof I was not permitted by any means to have) that I had divulged certain erroneous opinions, in which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159660:6"/>at a conference, I had given them no ſatisfaction, Whereas the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions in controverſie, were of their own divulging, and for ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I am perſwaded, I have given it in my anſwer, to this writing many ſubſcribed, with what willingneſſe I will not diſpute, though ſome much ſtuck at it, that afterwards ſubmitted to it, the dore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing purpoſely ſhut, and none ſuffered to go forth till he had ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, which ſome ſuſpecting refuſed to be there, this ſubſcription ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of all forts preſent refuſed, and for it were much reproached, nay, threatned; the reaſon of this ſubſcription was, their reſolution through the helpe of the Governour, as was openly profeſſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſend mee up to the Parliament or Aſſembly the next day: to whom indeed I had appealed, and do yet appeale to them, and all faithfull men, for a juſtification of the doctrine, I had eyther taught or writ. Thereupon it was told them that refuſed to ſubſcribe, that a Declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was expected from them of the reaſons why, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall men refuſing to ſubſcribe were <hi>Maſter Joanes</hi> of <hi>Hereford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> one of the Committee for <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> Maſter Alderman <hi>Hill</hi> of that City, Maſter <hi>Cloſe</hi> an ancient grave Miniſter, Maſter <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joh</hi> an honeſt Lawyer, Maſter <hi>Ketchman</hi> a Gentleman, and divers others.</p>
            <p>Afterwards there was much contention and mighty reaſoning among perſons of all conditions about the matters in controverſie, ſome affirming one thing, and ſome another, according as they did apprehend, but the manner of the carriage of this buſineſſe was generally complained of, affirming their proceedings againſt mee were neyther Chriſtian nor juſtifiable by the law of civill ſociety, and this <hi>Maſter Shepherd</hi> himſelfe confeſt at the evening of that day, and therefore told me hee could have wiſht it had been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; yet he with the Major of the City in the evening, privatly in the Committee room, ſpent a long time in perſwading mee to depart that place, affirming, that if I were the moſt orthodox Preacher in <hi>England,</hi> I were not a fit man for <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> which to mee ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med very ſtrange, that orthodox preaching, or which is all one, a Preacher that is orthodox, ſhould be a burthen too heavy for <hi>Gloceſter</hi> to beare, yet this poſition of theirs, an ancient man belonging to the Committee (if I miſtake not, it was the father of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159660:7"/>
               <hi>M. Holford</hi> the Miniſter) illuſtrated by a ſtory and ſimilitude of a Gentleman that had a very good woman to his wife, which yet he would often ſay, was no bleſſing at all unto him: ſo I might be a Preacher good enough, and have eſteem elſwhere, but if I ſhould ſtay in <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> I ſhould be no bleſſing at all unto it, I was indeed willing to depart, but for divers reaſons at that time I could not, neither indeed was it, as the caſe ſtood, meet I ſhould: for then it might have been truly ſaid, that I had deſerted mine owne cauſe, or rather Chriſts, in turning my back upon the Doctrine I taught, as if it had not been true and warrantable by the Scriptures. They therefore not prevailing with me: On the next Lords day there came an Order from the Governour, directed to the ſeverall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to be read in the pulpit after Sermon, to this purpoſe as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that whereas ſome doubted of the approvedneſſe of their proceedings in my two laſt appearances before the next day, ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in that as likewiſe in the queſtions that were put to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Bacon,</hi> ſhould be given before all the people at the Colledge, in a publique diſputation, which ſhould begin about eight of the clock, while the Pſalme was in ſinging the Gouernours man came to me, hearing <hi>Maſter Hart,</hi> and gave me warning to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare the next morning at the Colledge. What was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended I knew not well, or whereunto this would grow, and therefore with many thoughts of heart, which lodged with me that night, I came the next day at the time and place appointed where the <hi>Governour</hi> and <hi>Maſter Brummidge</hi> of the Committee newly come to towne, with much curteſie ſpake to mee and enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelves to protect mee from ſlander and wrong, which the one heard, and the other ſaw, I formerly ſuſteined, the people of all ſorts being come together to a great multitude, I being diſpoſed of by the <hi>Governour</hi> in the Quire, to ſtand oppoſite to mine oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Maſter Corbet,</hi> who ſtood on the otherſide: the <hi>Governour, Committee, Major,</hi> and other chief men in the midſt by a table ſet there to that end. At my elbow there ſtood a Marſhall with his Holbert (though I confeſſe, I did not obſerve it) of purpoſe if it might be to daunt me, as I afterwards heard, but God was with me, and through his power mine adverſaries fell before mee, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159660:7"/>Diſputation continued from eight till wel-nigh or altogether one, to the great contentment and ſatisfaction of the believing and more ſober-minded people, becauſe there was clcered before them, the objections made againſt mee, that mine innocency now appeared even to the convincing of thoſe that led away by others opinion had before a prejudice againſt me, this the ſtanders by can witneſſe, but the diſcontent that appeared even in the faces of mine oppoſers was very remarkable, that <hi>Maſter Corbet</hi> himſelf confeſſed, before all the people, that it had been better they had never begun ſuch a task as this, for the people will run ſaid hee after him much more then before, <hi>ſo the laſt errour ſhall be worſe then the firſt,</hi> this hee ſpake when hee ſaw the people give audience with reſpect to what I ſaid, and therefore complained of it to the <hi>Governour,</hi> but with no ſucceſſe. For the evidence of the truth, had for the preſent ſtruck a deep ſilence in all my oppoſers, which yet increaſed the envy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me: for ſome were that day complained of by witneſſes, that they had vowed to be the death of me; this day only five of thoſe ten Queſtions were made an end of, the other five left to the next day, but many thought, and I with them, that that field would nere be pitcht againe, becauſe of their ſo great diſappointment the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as alſo becauſe the remayning part of <hi>M. Corbets</hi> reply was far leſſe to the purpoſe then that which had gon before, it containing little elſe then invectives againſt my perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which could not but have an ill ſavour in ſuch an audience; yet the next day wee came toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe, where the advantage I had in reſpect of the matter in Controverſie was much loſt to me, in reſpect of the diſcountenance that was given mee, as all preſent might moſt evidently obſerve, which gave oceaſion to <hi>Maſter Cartwright,</hi> Treaſurer (as I take it) of that Gariſon to upbraid them publikely of partiality, for which he was bid to depart by <hi>Maſter Broughton,</hi> though by the <hi>Governour</hi> he was afterwards perſwaded to ſtay it out, yet God upheld me in this conflict alſo, that in concluſion no errour or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eariage whatſoever could be faſtned upon me, the Committee being judge, in the name of which I ſuppoſe, <hi>Maſter Brummidge,</hi> who was principal in the management of this buſines, drawing up care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully the reſult of each days Diſpute, gave the whole Aſſembly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159660:8"/>that there was nothing proved againſt me, but what was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Orthodox opinion, but this would not give mine accuſers ſatisfaction, and therefore <hi>Maſter Corbet</hi> with much vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency exclaimed that I had another meaning, whereunto it was gravely, though in other words replyed, that my meaning could not be judged in that Court, it being ſaid by <hi>M. Brummidge</hi> its beyond our power, to judge any man for his meaning; but becauſe nothing of fact could be proved, I muſt ſuffer for my meaning. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Miniſters that afternoon got themſelves into a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, from which were excluded by conſent <hi>Maſter Hart</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Cloſe,</hi> two grave and approved men, beſide ſome others that did exclude themſelves in, which it was very ſuddenly agreed upon, that of neceſſity I muſt depart the City, and give place to them, or elſe (as it was given out) they themſelves would leave the City, wherefore to gratifie them (as it is under the hand of ſome of the Committee) there was brought an Order to me by the Governours Clerk, wherein I was enjoyned the next day to depart the City, <hi>that they might reigne as Kiugs there,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of thoſe in <hi>Corinth,</hi> that tooke upon them in the like manner: but I muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, for they had a law to condemne me, though they firſt openly judged me innocent. Of this order I very earneſtly deſired a Copy (which they ſay will be granted in any Court in <hi>England</hi>) but by ſpeciall command, it was denyed me, onely I might ſee it, and read it, but take no copie of it, this I deſired, that I might have to ſhew the reaſons of my forced departure, not obtaining it from the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, I applyed my ſelfe to the Committee by way of Petition, wherein I made bold to lay at their feet certain conſiderations to move them, either to reverſe their firſt Order, or give me a Copie of it, together with reaſons why otherwiſe I could not actively obey, but muſt paſſively undergo, what they thought meet to inflict, which I preſented with my own hands: But there was after ſome conſultation a ſecond writing drawn up (there being two members of the Committee more now in Town then before) by the major part of the Committee, ſome of them denying their conſent, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they did deſire me to obey their firſt Order, a copie of which. I could not procure. I ſtayed two dayes after this in Town, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159660:8"/>rather to ſuffer impriſonment there, then to expoſe my ſelfe to inevitable dangers abroad, in which time I had diverſe meſſages<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to me from the Governour by ſeverall Officers and Souldiers to depart, and ſome grievous threatnings given me, to all which I gave anſwer, that when I had horſe and other conveniences, oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of company, and a Certificate that I might paſſe ſafely, I would be gone, whereupon on Saturday in the ſame week about two of the clock in the afternoon there came unexpectedly the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Lievtenant of the Governours troop, with a party of horſe to the door of my lodging, when they came in to me, they told me they were ſorry that it fell on them to be employed in ſuch a ſervice, yet being under command they muſt obey, and the word of command they had from the Governour, they ſaid, was, that I without delay muſt go with them, to whom I replyed, ſith tis ſo, I ſhall yield my ſelf to God, and you, to be diſpoſed of, as the Governour had given them command, wherefore immediatly taking my leave of Wife and Friends, I went with them, but finding ſome diſlike with the horſe appointed for me, the Captain Lievtenant, as alſo Captaine <hi>Maſſie</hi> then Governour of <hi>Sudely</hi> Caſtle (to which place I was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed that night) engaged themſelves I ſhould have the beſt horſe could be got in town for me, and they did accordingly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh me with an able horſe, which they put into my hands; this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which the Captain Lievtenant commanded, had me three miles out of town, where he left me, with the horſe appointed for mee, to the guidance of the head Corporall of the troop, and one troo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per more, both honeſt men, to bring me ſafely to <hi>Sudely</hi> Caſtle that night, which they did, though it was reported I ſhould have come there in the company of the Governour of the Caſtle, but he ſtayed behinde, and came not home till ſomwhat later in the night, but being there, I was very courteouſly entertained by him and his Lieutenant, and preached there upon requeſt the next day in the afternoon, being the Lords day: The Monday morning the Governour of the Caſtle gave command to the Corporall and Trooper to goe with, and guide me ſafe to <hi>Warwick,</hi> leaving the horſe ſtill in my hands, whence being brought in the way ſome miles, by the Lieutenant of the Caſtle the next day betimes in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159660:9"/>morning wee came ſafe to <hi>Warwick,</hi> where after ſome refreſhing my two Guides left me, having a command to go ſo far and no farther; of whom I demanded what ſhould be done with the horſe, they told me, they had no order concerning it, but told me it was in my diſpoſall, in ſo much that they did indeavour to exchange it for me, becauſe it went very hard, but this I kept, and after a while rod on it to <hi>London,</hi> where I kept it a while, till it was laid claim to by the wife of Colonell <hi>Okey,</hi> to whom after a certificate from <hi>Gloceſter</hi> from the Captain there, I delivered, this I mention in all the particulars of it, becauſe ſome in <hi>Gloceſter</hi> (that they might glory in, and increaſe my reproach) gave out that I went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to defraud them of the horſe, which notwithſtanding was put into my hands, with no hint of returning it, yea, it was often told me by the Officers and Souldiers, the Governour had given it me, which if it had been, it could not have countervailed the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage I ſuſtained in that place: This is a true Relation, God is witneſſe, and the conſciences of thoſe that were (as there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) preſent.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A Copie of the Letter I preſented to Colonel <hi>Maſsie</hi> Governour of <hi>Gloceſter, July,</hi> 1644. being ſuſpended from preaching there, by Maſter <hi>Web,</hi> then Major of the City, upon the information of M. <hi>Marſhall,</hi> as M. <hi>Holford</hi> reported, but upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty of M. <hi>Holford,</hi> as the Major himſelfe told me in the Committee room; I had my liberty by this Letter, which was as followeth.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Honoured Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LEt the juſt requeſt of the meaneſt of the ſervants of Chriſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of you, whoſe perſon and Doctrine ſcandalized, by either the malice or miſ-underſt anding of ſome, whereby his freedome in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:159660:9"/>Miniſtry (which he hath exerciſed with a good conſcieuce, and with the approbation of many wiſe and Godly of almoſt all degrees, well nigh this eight or ten years, excepting one quarters ſuffering by the now ſuppreſſed Prelates immediately before this ſo deſired Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament began, and this laſt three quarters baniſhment, into which he was driven through the loſſe of</hi> Briſtol, <hi>in which time, as many of note can witneſſe, be hath not behaved himſelfe unſeently) hath been ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped here, even where he conceived to receive both countenance and encouragement, being as deep in this Cauſe, both in reſpect of his endeavour to further it, and his loſſes ſuſteined for it, as any of his quality whatſoever: He humbly requeſts, either his liberty in the exerciſe of his Miniſtry, or that his oppoſers that hinder may bee known, that his Doctrine which is dearer to him than his life, may by him be cleered to be orthodox, and witneſſed unto by all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and particularly by all the reformed Churches, in the number of which we profeſſe our ſelves to be, and this he knows, through the power of Chriſt, he ſhall be able to doe. Though with all ſubmiſſion to your Honours wiſdom, he conceives there not being any Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call power ſetled, of Miniſters meddle to ſuppreſſe others (I ſpeak not of thoſe in the Aſſembly) they doe it uncalled, though I count it moſt meet and Chriſtian (in the things within your Sphere) to lay myſelfe at your feet, in whom the ſole government of this Gariſon is moſt worthily and moſt ſuccesfully entruſted, yet humbly expecting ſhelter and publike liberty in the preaching of the Word, if opportunity be given, there being not any reaſons to the contrary according to juſtice proved yet againſt one eſpecially ſith at the times are, I have not elſewhere comfortably to ſubſiſt, I mean in the Miniſtry, which I labour by all me an still death to magnifie, and I ſee many Churches empty, and the people in many places wofully untaught, I pray God it be not laid to the charge of thoſe, who, I know not upon what preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inder it: But I willingly ſubmit my ſelfe to your juſt power, praying for the increaſe of your moſt admired ſucceſſe and honour, which is gone almoſt all the world over. And thus, moſt Noble Sir, I reſt,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Honours ſervant, in the bleſſed Goſpel, <hi>Robert Bacon.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <list>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:159660:10"/>
               <head>The ten Queſtions propounded to mee on the Lords Day after Evening Sermon in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours Chamber, in the preſence of many Citizens, Souldiers, Miniſters, &amp;c. <hi>July</hi> 1644.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>WHether the Morall Law be abrogated?</hi> Neg.</item>
               <item>2 <hi>Whether good works be a means</hi> to obtein <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</hi> Neg.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>Whether God be diſpleaſed with</hi> his people that are in Chriſt, <hi>for their ſins, we mean ſuch a people as are</hi> in the Covenant of Grace? Neg.</item>
               <item>4 <hi>Whether thoſe in the Covenant of grace, are to try their juſtification by their ſanctification?</hi> Affir.</item>
               <item>5 <hi>Whether faith be a Condition of the New Covenant?</hi> Neg.</item>
               <item>6 <hi>Whether godly ſorrow for ſin be required in ſuch a one a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is in the New Covenant?</hi> Affir.</item>
               <item>7 <hi>Whether Confeſsion of ſin</hi> (i.e.) <hi>of our originall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of our ſinfull actions, reckoning them up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord be required in a Chriſtian?</hi> Affir.</item>
               <item>8 <hi>Whether you hold Communion with the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (i.e.) <hi>in our Parochiall Aſſemblies to be lawfull?</hi> Neg.</item>
               <item>9 <hi>Whether Repentance</hi> be neceſſary [to] <hi>the forgivenes of ſins?</hi> Neg.</item>
               <item>10 <hi>Whether there be a reall change in the perſon that is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</hi> Affir.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:159660:10"/>Theſe Queſtions were ſo propoſed by us.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johan. Holford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Williel. Hodges.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Corbet.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And <hi>thus anſwered</hi> by <hi>Maſter Bacon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though indeed forcedly, and ſomwhat otherwiſe then upon due conſideration, hee would have done, there being not ſufficient time given to conſider of them, and therefore they were ſubſcribed only thus on condition, that afterwards time might be given, in writing to make out my underſtanding of them.</p>
            <p>On the Wedneſday morning following, betwixt eight and nine of clock, in the roome where the Councell of War was kept, I delivered into the hands of the Governour, Colonel <hi>Maſsie,</hi> (where were preſent as before, many Gentlemen, Souldiers, Citizens, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Town and Country, beſides the Committee and Major of the City): this Anſwer in theſe words following word for word.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the moſt Noble Governour of <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and the Honourable Committee of Parliament in <hi>Gloceſter.</hi> An Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>TO thoſe ten Queſtions, which by the authority of the moſt Noble Governour of <hi>Gloceſter, (John Holford, William Hodges, John Corbet Miniſters propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded)</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:159660:11"/>by whoſe ſole authority I anſwer, in ſome of which Queſtions we agree as in the firſt, fourth, ſixth, ſeventh, tenth, in the reſt we differ, at leaſt in expreſſion: I have anſwered briefly to them all, as the Lord gave me time and knowledge, and as I was able lying under ſo many preſſures and reproches, which God in due time will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move (I know) in the meane time there is need of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; my Anſwer is as followeth.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="question">
                     <head>1 <hi>Whether the Morall Law be abrogated?</hi> Neg.</head>
                     <p>For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1 The Law morall was revealed from Heaven, of God himſelf on Mount <hi>Sinay,</hi> and therefore in that conſideration to be had in high honour and account of all.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Its part of the holy Scriptures, and therefore never to be ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but highly to he regarded by the whole Church of God.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 It is the very image of God, ſo that by the Law morall, wee may ſee the holineſſe and righteouſneſſe of God.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Chriſt himſelfe was ſhadowed forth in the Law, for by the law wee ſee what a one Chriſt is, and was to be, even ſuch a one, as hath as much righteouſneſſe as the Law requires.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 All the world ſhall be judged by it at the laſt day.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 The Law in the hand of a Mediator is the rule of life, for what the law doth command in the letter vvithout, that the lavv of the ſpirit of life, doth vvork vvithin, vvhich is therefore called the lavv of faith, or the lavv of Chriſt, or the lavv vvritten in the heart.</p>
                     <p n="7">7 Thoſe that believe in Jeſus vvalke more freely and more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in the things contained in, and enjoyned by the lavv, then they that are altogether under the lavv, and vvithout Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="8">8 The lavv is exceeding uſefull to take luen off from that dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable opinion of their ovvn righteouſneſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="question">
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:159660:11"/>
                     <head>2 <hi>Whether good works be a means to</hi> obtein <hi>ſalvation?</hi> Neg.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 I doe altogether reject this expreſſion, as moſt unſavorie and unbeſteming the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Yet, I affirme, that it is as impoſſible to divide good works from faith, I mean, that which is ſaving, as it is to divide the light from the Sun, or heat from the fire, for ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>We are created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, which God hath prepared that we ſhould walke in them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 To affirme that good works are a means to <hi>obtein ſalvation,</hi> is in effect to deny, that Chriſt is the onely means to obtein ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for <hi>Salvation is by Chriſt onely.</hi> Act. 4.12.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="question">
                     <head>3 <hi>Whether God be diſpleaſed</hi> with his people that are in Chriſt <hi>for their ſins,
<note place="margin">Gods wel plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with us [in Chriſt] and therefore (which is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite) not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpleaſed with us [in him,] beſides, our ſins are done away [in him,] <hi>(ergo)</hi> not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpleaſed with us for ſin [in him [to be in a covenant of grace or favour and yet to be even in that covenant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der disfavour or diſpleaſure, ſeems to me a contradiction.</note> we mean ſuch a people as are</hi> in the Covenaut of Grace. Neg.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 When we affirme that God is diſpleaſed, or is angry, we all confeſſe that it is ſpoken after the manner of men, for God is not ſubject to paſſion as men are, onely through our weakneſſe we doe ſo think, and therefore the Scriptures ſo ſpeak.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Even when we are chaſtned of the Lord, it is an argument of his love, and not of his diſpleaſure, and therefore the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>Whons the Lord loveth he chaſtreth,</hi> the Philoſopher would not beat his ſervant in anger, and if it bee condemned in men why ſhould it be affirm'd of God, <hi>Fathers and maſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ers for a few dayes, chaſtned us after their own pleaſure, but he for our profit, that we might be partakers of his holineſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 'Tis moſt peremptorily to be affirmed that God hates ſin in whomſoever it is, even in his own Son, though it was not his, but ours, and therefore alſo he muſt needs hate it in his own children.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 So far forth as the children of God live off from Chriſt, and walke unworthy of the Goſpel, ſo far forth they lie under ſence of vvrath, in ſo much as the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>He ſcourgeth every ſon he loves:</hi> it is not the will of God, nay, 'tis impoſſible that a man ſhould have peace in the wayes of ſin, then the devills and wicked
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159660:12"/>men might have peace, from vvhom the vvay of peace is hid.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 There are but two vvayes the one of ſin, and ſo of death and ſorrovv, even vvhen the Saints vvalke in that vvay, they have no more peace, nay, for the preſent not ſo much, as the vvicked have, and they have no true peace at all. 2 The way of wiſdom, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Whoſe ways are ways of pleaſantneſſe, and all her paths are peace,</hi> who ſo walks in that way, and ſo far forth as he walks in that way, ſhall never want peace.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 So there are two ways by which God hath made himſelfe known in the Scriptures, and is known at this day among men: The firſt is by the Law onely, ſo the naturall man knows God and no otherwiſe ſo that ſo far forth as he keeps the Law, ſo far forth he apprehends he pleaſeth God, <hi>i.e.</hi> as he looks upon him in the law; and again, ſo far as he comes ſhort of obedience to the Law, ſo far he apprehends he diſpleaſeth God, as he is known in the Law <hi>i.e.</hi> out of Chriſt, and it is ſo as he apprehends. 2 God hath made known himſelfe to us in Chriſt, and ſo he is <hi>well pleaſed</hi> with us <hi>in him, Mat.</hi> 3.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>in whom I amwell pleaſed,</hi> to this all the Scriptures beare witneſſe, <hi>Whom he loves, he loves unto the end,</hi> for he loves them for Chriſts ſake, and not for their own and loves them as much at one time as at another, now Chriſt for whoſe ſake God loves us, <hi>is yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever,</hi> and therefore ſo muſt needs Gods love to us be in him: God forbid that we ſhould affirme that God is up and down with us in his love, indeed a man, yea, a believer, to the diſhonour of God, doth too frequently thinke ſo, but his thoughts are not as our thoughts, onely it's moſt true, that through ſin the ſoule is ſomtimes ſo clouded, and miſted, that it cannot ſee its way to God, neither the light of his countenance ſhining upon him, but apprehends himſelfe under wrath, judging himſelfe by the Law, as he cannot eaſily otherwiſe doe, for as <hi>Luther</hi> ſpeaks, it is no eaſie thing to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Chriſt and his righteouſneſſe, and Gods love to us in him at ſuch a time: So far as naturall we judge our ſelves by the Law, but ſo far as ſpirituall we ſee our ſelves accepted of God in Chriſt, by the Law we ſee our ſelves loſt, by Chriſt revealed in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel we ſee our ſelves juſtified, by the firſt we are ſinners, by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159660:12"/>righteous, this is judged orthodox by <hi>Luther,</hi> and I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by all other ſo ber men.</p>
                     <p n="7">7 As for our perſons, God loved us when we were yet ſinners, Chriſt dyed for us when we were enemies, therefore, <hi>being recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled,
<note place="margin">
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </note> we ſhall be ſaved from wrath through him (that is)</hi> from that anger, as the word from the Originall may be read, meaning from that wrath or anger which was due unto us by the Law, and therefore he adds in that <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.11. Not onely ſo, but we boaſt or <hi>joy in God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom we have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the atonement,</hi> in ſo much that Doctor <hi>Sibbs</hi> affirms, that a man well acquainted with the doctrine of reconciliation to God in Chriſt, may even goe ſinging to heaven.</p>
                     <p n="8">8 I have uſed the more words about this queſtion, becauſe the manner of the propoſall, I confeſſe, is not ſo warrantable by the Scriptures, therefore when it was delivered thus <hi>(Whether God be diſpleaſed with the ſins of his people.)</hi> I affirmed it, but being thus delivered, I denyed it, leaſt it ſhould be thought, that God, with whom there is <hi>no variableneſſe, or ſhadow of change,</hi> ſhould be unconſtant in his love to his elect, whom he hath choſen to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="question">
                     <head>4 <hi>Whether thoſe in the Covenant of Grace are to try their juſtification by their ſanctification?</hi> Affir.</head>
                     <p>For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1 No man knows his juſtification, till he findes in himſelfe in ſome meaſure of ſanctification or holineſſe, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> that ſeed of God which <hi>John</hi> ſayes <hi>abides in him that is borne of God,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. For what is done without a man, in <hi>foro Coeli</hi> (as they ſpeake) in the high Court of heaven, that is done in time within, in <hi>foro conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae,</hi> in the lower Court of our own conſciences, by the ſpirit of Chriſt which is given unto us: now where the ſpirit of Chriſt is, there are the fruits of the ſpirit, and the fruit of the ſpirit is, in all goodneſſe, and righteouſneſſe and truth, yea, <hi>and much aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> 1 Theſ. 1.5.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 But to affirme, when I doe ſome good actions, I muſt believe my juſtification, and when I faile in ſome actions (as who faileth not) I muſt ſuſpect my juſtification, and ſo to meaſure my juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159660:13"/>by my acts of ſanctification, and works which I have done, I doe utterly deny, as tending to overthrow the moſt glorious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of juſtification, for in time of temptation, I ſee nothing but ſin and death, at ſuch a time, <hi>againſt hope I believe in hope,</hi> that I am juſtified, and that is the heighth and glory of faith, as <hi>Luther</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably ſpeaks.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Yet this I profeſſe, The more a man is aſſured of his juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, the more he doth abound in all the wayes and works of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtſication, and holineſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="question">
                     <head>5 <hi>Whether Faith be a condition of the new Covenant?</hi> Neg.</head>
                     <p>For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1 This is one difference betwixt the Covenant of works, and the Covenant of Grace, the one promiſeth life upon condition, the other gives it of free promiſe, the firſt commands much, and gives nothing, but blows upon default, the other commands no more then it gives.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 We are not, required to the ratification of the Covenant, to bring faith to God,
<note place="margin">It goes indeed for currant among many, that faith is the condition of the New Covenant, but how many inconveniences comes in thereby, experience ſhews: Some learned men therefore judge it to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, more meet to call it a branch of the New Covenant. Faith in the New Covenant is <hi>the work of God, Iohn</hi> 6. it being indeed a work meet for God, but infinitely too hard for man, therefore <hi>the gift of God.</hi> Epheſ. 2.8.</note> but the Covenant is to give us faith to bring us to God, ſo that faith is a branch of the new Covenant; for if God ſhould ſtay to make good his Covenant till we bring faith to the Covenant, the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant would be of none effect, therefore the Covenant doth not depend upon our belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, but upon Gods promiſe and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>If we believe not, yet he abideth faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and cannot deny himſelfe.</hi> 2 Tim. 2.13.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 In the new Covenant God ties him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and not the creature, we are in his keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not our own, or elſe our condition were now, as it was before in <hi>Adam,</hi> which no Chriſtian will affirme, onely faith is urged in the miniſtry of the Goſpel, and in urging of it, it is given to them that ſhall be ſaved, becauſe no man is juſtified in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience before God, till be doth believe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="question">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:159660:13"/>
                     <head>6 <hi>Whether godly ſorrow for ſin be required in ſuch a one, as is in the New Covenant?</hi> Affir.</head>
                     <p>For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1 It is by all meanes to be required in caſe of ſin, of one in the Covenant of grace, ſuch a one, in ſuch a caſe, is by all kindes of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to be exhorted thereunto.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Sorrow of its ſelfe is not to be urged upon him, therefore the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>I rejoyced not that yee were made ſorry:</hi> but that ſorrow which the Apoſtle calls <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, or godly ſorrow, ſorrow according to godlineſſe, is by all means in the caſe above ſaid to be preſſed, and therefore the Apoſtle doth in effect affirme, that he did rejoyce that they ſorrowed, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which he opens in the next words, <hi>Yee ſorrowed,</hi> ſayth he, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, according to God, or after a godly manner: Now in what the Apoſtle rejoyced, we alſo may rejoyce in, in the behalfe of others.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Yet, I utterly deny it in this ſenſe, as if it were ſo required, that the Covenant of grace did depend upon it, we doe it not to that end, but becauſe the Covenant is immutable, and cannot but be fulfilled, therefore we doe it, for it is a part of the Covenant to leade us out unto it, therefore that may be the underſtanding of that phraſe of <hi>godly ſorrow,</hi> becauſe it is the work of God in us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="question">
                     <head>7 <hi>Whether confeſsion of ſin</hi> (i.e.) <hi>of our originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and of our ſinfull actions, reckoning them up before the Lord, be required in a Chriſtian?</hi> Affir.</head>
                     <p>For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1 This I have taught publikely, and therefore need not ſpeake more, the words in effect were theſe, Phariſees and Plypocrites may confeſſe their <hi>ſinfull actions,</hi> but they are not wont to confeſſe <hi>their ſinfulneſſe,</hi> but the Saints confeſſe not onely their <hi>ſinfull actions,</hi> but alſo <hi>their ſinfulneſſe,</hi> they doe not onely ſee their actions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, but their very natures, and doe bewayle their natures more
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159660:14"/>then their actions, becauſe their evill natures are thoſe corrupt Fountains, whence flow theſe ſoule ſtreams.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 The confeſſion of the Saints is grounded upon the knowledge of Gods love in Chriſt, but the confeſſion of Hypocrites is upon ſome other information and grounds.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="question">
                     <head>8
<note n="(a)" place="margin">How dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult it is to decermine what the Church of <hi>England</hi> is, we may learn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                           <hi>Smectymnius.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Whether you hold communion with the Church of</hi> England? (i.e.) <hi>in our parochiall Aſſemblies to be lawfull?</hi> Neg.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 It is a matter that concerns diſcipline, and that
<note n="(b)" place="margin">This was given in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Iuly</hi> 1644</note> queſtion is not yet reſolved upon in the Kingdom,
<note place="margin">That every Pariſh Affembly, ſhould beare the name of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſeems ſtrange to me, for many Pariſhes know not what the Church of <hi>England</hi> means. 2 Though there may bee Churches in many Pariſhes in <hi>England,</hi> yet they are not Churches as Pariſhes, or Pariſhes, and therefore Churches: Pariſhes, as is confeſt, are but of late, and hamane invention, but by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (I ſuppoſe) is underſtood, either all the people in <hi>England,</hi> as they are by law enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to confeſſe the ſame Doctrine, and practice the ſame Diſcipline, and in this ſence the Church of <hi>England,</hi> eſpecially in reſpect of diſcipline, is ceaſing, or ceaſed, to be what it was, therefore by the Church of <hi>England</hi> I hold it ſafeſt to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all, of all conditions, that have indeed faith towards our Lord Ieſus, and ſo are the Church of God in the eye of God, and are of a ſutable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation towards men in practice, and God in profeſſion, of this Church I rejoyce that I am a member, and with it delight to have commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</note> the work of reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not finiſhed, and ſcarce at all begun in ſome places and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 For ought I know the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have not repented them of their falſe worſhips, and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable proſtituting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the will and ways of the Prelates, for which the Land, polluted with ſo much Idolatry, Atheiſme, and prophaneſſe, is now even made drunke with bloud.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Yet I ſhall have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with any people, in any Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, ſo far as reformed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="question">
                     <head>9 <hi>Whether Repentance be neceſſary
<note place="margin">[To] <hi>(i.e.)</hi> To bring in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> the word ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently ſounds.</note> the remiſsion of Sins?</hi> Neg.</head>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:159660:14"/>
                     <p n="1">1 It is an unſavoury, unſafe, and unſound expreſſion,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Repentance is either legall or Evangelicall as M. <hi>Perkins</hi> and others diſtinguiſh: Now legall repentance in theſe dayes of the increaſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is confeſſedly not neceſſary to the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſins, the unreaſonable urging of it, is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be one cauſe that rendred the Miniſtry heretofore ſo unprofitable, requiring qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to prepare for Chriſt, men conceiving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to have ability to furniſh themſelves ſo, as to be judged meet, even of God himſelfe, to give entertainment to his Son. Now the Queſtion is underſtood of this ſort of repentance, I ſuppoſe, by them that propoſed it, which gave me occaſion ſo to expreſſe my ſelfe in the firſt Sect. But if they ment Evangelicall tepentance, yet remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſins mnſt needs precede, for remiſſio of ſins cannot be the wages of repentance as it ſeems to be, if it did go before: This is then the order. 1 The Goſpel is preached, the ſum of which, is the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſins. Then 2 It is recived in the Spirit through be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving. 3 Then comes <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> The change of the minde, repentance towards God, as a fruit of faith in the Lord Ieſus, in the which change of minde there are ever theſe foure things. 1 A right knowledge and high eſteem of God. 2 A right knowledge and high account of Chriſt, as the onely way to God, to finde acceptance with him. 3 A right underſtanding of our ſelves, as loved of, and reconciled to God in Chriſt. 4 A right underſtanding and infinite loathing of our ſelves, as we are in our ſelves, denying and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring our ſelves, and ſins, the world and things below, for Chriſts ſake.</note> borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring nigh unto, if not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther agreeing with that of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi> who affirms that repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is a way unto faith, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification in the remiſſion of ſins, which Maſter <hi>Willet</hi> in his <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſis,</hi> in his fourteenth generall controverſie of Popiſh penance confutes.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Repentance is not before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins, as this queſtion imports, for that which is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to remiſſion of ſins, muſt be before remiſſion of ſins, is, as we muſt walke in the way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee come to the journies end: now repentance is not the way to remiſſion of ſins as <hi>Willet</hi> againſt <hi>Bellarmine</hi> proves, but the fruit of remiſſion of ſins, for remiſſion of ſins is in order of nature before repentance, as all orthodox men I thinke confeſſe, though both at the ſame time in every true believer.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 There is no remiſſion of ſins beleeved, after which, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon which, doth not follow true repentance: yet remiſſion of ſins doth not depend upon repentance, but repentance upon remiſſion of ſins.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="question">
                     <head>10 <hi>Whether there be a reall change in the perſon that is ſaved?</hi> Affir.</head>
                     <p>This I have both publikely and privatly cleered and proved, and ſhall yet further cleer and prove when God ſhall open a way again unto me.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:159660:15"/>Thus much for the preſent, I conceive, as touching theſe perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, wherein I have ſpoken <hi>(my conſcience bearing mee witneſſe in the holy Ghoſt)</hi> what I underſtand to be the minde of God in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, and the judgment of the Orthodox Churches at this day, and this not as pleaſing men but God, referring my ſelfe to all the godly learned, all the World over, for judgment herein.</p>
                     <p>What ever are the apprehenſions of men concerning me, as they are very various and ſtrange, neither in word or deed, no, not in thought, have I intended, or ſhewed any diſrepect to any man, as far as I know, that differs from me in judgment, but have behaved my ſelf with all good Conſcience, both towards God and men, I can ſpeak no more then I know, neither ſhall I willingly ſpeak leſſe.</p>
                     <p>My humble requeſt to all the Saints and Miniſters of God is, that, whereunto <hi>we have attained, we may walk by the ſame rule,</hi> for it is impoſſible that wee ſhould in all things, and in all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, be of the ſame minde, therefore let us not by any means op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe each others ſpirit, for no man can well ſpeake more then hee knows, or confeſſe more then hee believes: let the words of the Apoſtle be alwayes ſounding in our eares, as if hee were now ſpeaking unto us, as hee was ſometimes to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, Rom.</hi> 12.3. <hi>I ſay, through the grace given to mee, to every man that is among you, not to think of himſelf more highly then he ought to think, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, but to thinke to ſobriety according as God hath dealt to every man the meaſure of faith:</hi> which rule if neglected, 'tis impoſsible there ſhould be peace, not only in the World, but even in the Church, for there are diverſities of apprehenſions, even of the ſame things, every one <hi>ſpeaking according to the meaſure of the gift of Christ.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If this do not ſatisfie, I expect mine Opponents anſwer in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, becauſe they are many, and I in a manner alone, beſides, <hi>litera ſcript a manet,</hi> yet afterwards I ſhall not refuſe conference with any, that ſhall with meekneſſe deſire it:</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>July 16, 1644.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Robert Bacon.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Wedneſday following the two publique diſputes held in the Colledge, there was ſent an Order (after that ſome of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:159660:15"/>had been in conſultation together) from ſome of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, who had the day before publikely taken off the charge of errour M. <hi>Cerbet</hi> and others layed againſt me, (in which alſo they did acquit me as from the matter of errour yet enjoyned me therein to depart the next day, a copy of which I could not get, neither could then actively obey: I humbly preſented to them my reaſons, which were, word, for word, as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Honourable Committee of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in <hi>Gloceſter.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honourable,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHereas I have ſeen an Order agreed upon by ſome of the Committee, that I am to depart this City to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, being Thurſday, the five and twentieth of this inſtant moneth, not to reſide in any Gariſon of this County, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command of the Governonr of</hi> Gloceſter, <hi>wherein if I fail, I am to expect puniſhment from the Committee, I humbly crave leave to lay at your feet, theſe following Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 I have ſuffered in the cauſe of the Parliament, the loſſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove four hundred pounds in money and goods, unleſſe I can reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it again in the time of peace, ſo that I expect in juſtice, from the honourable Parliament (I contiraring faithfull unto them as I ſhall through the helpe of God, till death) liberty and livelihood under their protection, which I beg for at your hands, their repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative, here.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 I have not wherewithall, neither can I poſſibly with the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and health of my perſon depart ſo ſuddenly from this Gariſon.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 This I know, that if I fall into the hands of the Kings for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, unleſſe God doth mightily deliver me, will endanger the taking away of my life by them, for God is witneſſe, and many men, how I have endevoured by all means to further the cauſe of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, againſt them.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:159660:16"/>4 By this Order it cannot othervviſe appeare, but that I am put out of the City as a Malignant, vvhich if I am apprehended, ſo to be, I am infinitely vvronged, for I never entertained the leaſt thought of diſreſpect againſt the Parliament.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 I have behav'd my ſelf, both before, and ſince I came to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, vvith all good conſcience, both tovvards God and men, ſaying, no other thing, but vvitneſſing both to ſmall, and great, vvhat Chriſt, the Apoſtles, and Martyrs, and our firſt Reformers vvitneſſed, and all the Proteſtant Churches, at this day.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 I am not ſuch a ſtranger, but I am knowne to many of good report in the City, beſides, I have lived till after <hi>Briſtoll</hi> vvas taken, a publike Preacher, in, and about that City (vvhich is not far from this) eight or nine yeers.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 Whether it be not an infringing of the liberty of the ſubject, to thruſt mee out of the City for matters of Religion, eſpecially, when all that have been ſpoken or written by me, is in appearance truth, as is confeſſed, no errour proved againſt mee, though many ſuſpected, my heart and thoughts being judged, when my actions are vvithout offence.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Whether mercy be not to be mingled with juſtice, that I be not forced to depart from my deare and loving wife (a woman of good birth and quality) eſpecially now ſhee is neere that perillous time of child-birth-bearing, grief, by reaſon of my forced departure (ſhe being but a vveak vvoman) may haſten her death, eſpecially in ſuch a caſe.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 Whether there be not an offence taken, and not given, by my preaching and converſation, as is uſuall, at the power and truth of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 Yet, if I muſt be put out of towne, I humbly beg a Copy of the Order, that I may have, to ſhew the reaſons why, and that I may have ſome longer time to prepare for ſo long a journey, for whether to goe but to the City of <hi>London,</hi> I know not, and that I may take the next opportunity for company.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, for the juſtification of my innocency, perſon, &amp; doctrine, I refer my ſelf to the tribunall of Gods juſtice and this moſt Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Parliament: deſiring God to forgive the malice and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:159660:16"/>of mine enemies. And thus I humbly take my leave, and reſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Honours ſervant in the bleſſed Goſpel: R. BACON.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>A Copy of the Order ſent me after the giving in this Petition.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>WE the Gentlemen of the Committee, gave out our Order, upon a ſerious debate, not by our ſelues (as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our inſtructions, we might have done) but with the</hi> ingredients <hi>and</hi> conſult <hi>of many</hi> godly <hi>and</hi> learned Miniſters; <hi>by</hi> both parties, <hi>and upon emergent reaſons our votes were concluded, and (in a more civill manner then Maſter</hi> Bacon <hi>deſerved) were ſent unto him; yet, although he hath rather arraigned then entreated the Committee for an alteration of our judgments, we are reſolved not to alter our commands, as rather</hi> engaged <hi>to</hi> gratifie <hi>ſo many</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Divines <hi>in this buſineſſe then his fancie; the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges we have received from his hands, we hold more ſit to be tranſmitted to the</hi> Parliament, <hi>as a greater abuſe to their</hi> Ordinance, <hi>then an offence to our perſons; and therefore</hi> deſire <hi>Maſter</hi> Bacon <hi>will be obedient to our former Order, rather then put us upon a ſecond courſe, which wee not ſo much deſire as he deſerves.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>What affinity ſome paſſages in this Order have with that in the <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.13. thoſe that have wiſdome from above, may conſider. Beſides, who to judge the moſt godly and orthodox Miniſters in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:159660:17"/>theſe days of Controverſie, is doubtleſſe, ſomewhat more difficult then is by moſt ſuppoſed, otherwiſe theſe glorious (that I ſay not vain-glorious titles (as <hi>godly, learned, orthodox,</hi>) would not have been ſo confidently put upon theſe Miniſters, whoſe doctrinall aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is moſt <hi>Heterodox,</hi> to name but that under their own hands, <hi>that by good works we obtein ſalvation,</hi> and whoſe practice in this was far enough from being <hi>godly,</hi> to undermine their <hi>brother,</hi> and ſeeke his ruine, to <hi>establiſh themſelves,</hi> not rendring him, no not the <hi>Magiſtrate himſelf,</hi> a juſt reaſon why.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <head>I ſhall here inſert (as an <hi>acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the ſympathy of a faithfull Friend, and Miniſter of the <hi>Goſpell</hi>) theſe few lines, which he in verſe ſent my wife, to ſupport her in her <hi>ſolitarines,</hi> and my forced departure.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>POſſeſſe your ſoule in</hi> patience, <hi>Chriſt doth</hi> reigne,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>His r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d ſhall</hi> feed, <hi>his</hi> ſtaffe <hi>ſhall you</hi> ſuſteine,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Is</hi> husband <hi>gon? do</hi> friends <hi>begin to</hi> hind?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Let not your heart be</hi> ſad, <hi>God will</hi> provide,</l>
                        <l>Life, livelihood, friends, husband, <hi>and withall:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Increaſe of</hi> honour, <hi>ſhall ſucceed your</hi> fall:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Paſſe by the</hi> frowns <hi>of men, contemne their</hi> ſcorn,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Be not diſmaid with</hi> bonds, <hi>you are free</hi> born,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>All things are ſubject unto</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and</hi> hee,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Commands them at his</hi> pleaſure, <hi>therefore wee,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of</hi> ſafety <hi>may be ſure,</hi> Chriſt <hi>for us is,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>No power, or hate,</hi> can hurt, <hi>thoſe that</hi> are his.</l>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:159660:17"/>The ſpark that was blown up into ſo great a flame againſt mee, was my publike reprehenſion of a certain pretended playſter for a <hi>Sin-ſick Soule,</hi> as being in it ſelf contradictory, and repugnant to that of the Lords own preſcribing, of which I ſpake from <hi>Jeremy</hi> the 32.6. which is made up of thoſe two ſweet and ſaving ſalves, <hi>Truth and Peace,</hi> both which as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks, but in a little different language, kiſſe each other in Chriſt, as alſo in them that are Chriſts, but becauſe I mentioned faith and repentance, which are two of thoſe more then twenty other ingredients in this Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanke medicine, ſome, whether inconſideratly or enviouſly, or both, I will not determine, reported, that I denied Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but let the Aſſembly, or others judge, whether the Authour of this Medicine, ſpeak not rather the language of <hi>Rome,</hi> then <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> vvhether he be not rather a ſtranger, then a home-bred Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, deceiving the people, feeding them vvith husks, under the ſpecious names of the <hi>Crums of Comfort,</hi> there being evidently in it, not only that vvhich is popiſh, falſe, and erroneous, but that vvhich renders Religion, and the Myſtery of God ridiculous; a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of which, that all may judge, is here inſcribed.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="remedy">
                        <head>A ſpeciall Remedy, for a <hi>Sin-ſick Soule.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>FIrſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Faſt and Pray,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">In a book calld the <hi>Crums of Comfort.</hi>
                           </note> 2 <hi>and then take a quart of Repentance of</hi> Nineve, <hi>and</hi> 3 <hi>put in two handfuls of faith</hi> 4 <hi>in the bloud of Chriſt, with as much</hi> 5 <hi>Hope and</hi> 6 <hi>Charity as you can get, and put it into a Veſſell of</hi> 7 <hi>a clean Conſcience,</hi> 8 <hi>then boyle it in the fire of love,</hi> 9 <hi>ſo long till you ſee by the Eyes of Faith, the black foam of the love of this World ſtinke in your ſtomacke,</hi> 10 <hi>then ſcum it off cleane, with the Spoone of faithfull Prayers, when this is done,</hi> 11 <hi>put in the Powder of Patience, and</hi> 12 <hi>take the Cloth of Chriſts Innocency,</hi> 13 <hi>and ſtrain altogether in his Cup,</hi> 14 <hi>then drink it burning hot next thy heart,</hi> 15 <hi>and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee warme with as many cloaths of the Amendment of life, as God ſhall ſtrengthen and enable thee to beare, that</hi> 16 <hi>thou
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:159660:18"/>mayst ſweat out all the poyſon of Covetouſneſſe, Pride, Whoredome, Idolatry, Uſury, Swearing, Lying, with ſuch like,</hi> 17 <hi>and when thou feeleſt thy ſelf altered from the forenamed vices. Take</hi> 18 <hi>the Powder of Say-well, and put it upon thy tongue,</hi> 19 <hi>but drinke thrice as much,
<note place="margin">☞</note> do well daily,</hi> 20 Then take the Oile of good works, and anoint therewith thine eyes, eares, heart and hands <hi>that they may be ready and nimble to miniſter to the poore members of Chriſt, when this is done, then in Gods name,</hi> 21 <hi>riſe from ſin willingly,</hi> 22 <hi>reade in the Bible daily, take up the Croſſe of Chriſt boldly,</hi> 24 <hi>and ſtand to it manfully,</hi> 25 <hi>bear all viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions patiently,</hi> 26 <hi>Pray continually,</hi> 27 <hi>Reſt thankefully, and thou ſhalt live everlaſtingly, and come to the hill of joy quickly, to to which place haſten us good Lord ſpeedily.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:159660:18"/>
            <head>A POSTCRIPT, <hi>Containing ſome generall and perticular Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations upon M.</hi> Edwards <hi>his</hi> Gangraena.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1 <hi>Generall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAſter <hi>Edwards</hi> with the helpe of others, that <hi>load to his mill,</hi> ſeeks to faſten reproach upon the perſons of thoſe, whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he never ſaw, and the errours he chargeth on them, <hi>hee cannot prove,</hi> yet his ayme, and perhaps, the iſſue of his calumnies, may prove to <hi>this Nation,</hi> or to many in it, of as dangerous, and as dreadfull conſequence, as was the inſinuation of the <hi>High-Prieſts and Phariſees</hi> againſt Chriſt, his perſon, Doctrine, converſation, followers, <hi>to the Jewiſh Nation,</hi> and many in it: for to this day, <hi>that people judge,</hi> as theſe men reported, that Chriſt was an <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> his Doctrine <hi>blaſphemous,</hi> his converſation <hi>looſe,</hi> his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <hi>accurſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt his entertainment at his comming in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> is fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told to hold proportion with that of his comming <hi>in the fleſh,</hi> and therefore as little to be diſcerned in the <hi>one,</hi> as in the <hi>other,</hi> becauſe he is to ſuffer over again in the Spirit, in the Goſpel, in ſome way of proportion <hi>in the Saints,</hi> as he did then in the fleſh, in his own perſon, <hi>for the Saints:</hi> here is wiſdom, and 'tis that which is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from above, to diſcerne the <hi>day of his comming,</hi> for he is in the world now, as then, under <hi>diſguiſes,</hi> as a ſigne to be <hi>ſpoken againſt,</hi> to be judged in his members a <hi>blaſphemer,</hi> a <hi>deceiver,</hi> a man <hi>glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenous,</hi> a friend of <hi>Publicans,</hi> and <hi>Sinners,</hi> a <hi>wine-bibber,</hi> yea, to be <hi>crucified,</hi> and put to <hi>open ſhame:</hi> and of this he will upbraid the world at his <hi>appearing,</hi> and comming; I was <hi>among you,</hi> but as <hi>hungry,</hi> and <hi>thirſty,</hi> and <hi>naked,</hi> and <hi>ſick,</hi> and <hi>impriſoned,</hi> wherefore you own'd me not in my meanneſſe, and low <hi>eſtate,</hi> therefore depart from me I know <hi>you not,</hi> I owne you not, you ſhall not, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, ſhare with me, and mine, in <hi>glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:159660:19"/>Men build the <hi>Sepulchers</hi> of the Prophets, ſeem to honour the memory of <hi>Chriſt, glory</hi> in the ſtory of the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> &amp; cal themſelvs after their <hi>names,</hi> and yet perſecute, blaſpheme, and ſpeake all manner of evill of <hi>that Spirit by which they ſpake,</hi> thus it was from the beginning, and it is ſo unto this <hi>preſent houre,</hi> thus the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſces ſtood they thought in the truth the Prophets <hi>dyed for,</hi> and yet were in their generation, open and profeſſed enemies <hi>unto it,</hi> and thus to this day, many contend in bitterneſſe, and wrath, to their own, and others trouble, yea, the trouble of the <hi>Land they live in,</hi> for the <hi>truth</hi> they thinke, and yet remain without it, yea, revile it, where it is in truth, <hi>having the forme,</hi> and <hi>not the power,</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and not the thing itſelfe (as they whom they pretend to be imitators of, had) which whereſoever it is, is blaſphemed, of them that have it not, though they <hi>pretend</hi> never ſo much to have it. But this in ſomeſort may be diſcerned, for by their fruits yee may know them, they that have it in pretence onely, are as others of the world are, excepting this pretence onely, <hi>proud, boaſters, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, falſe accuſers, make-bates, fierce, unquiet deſpiſers of them that are good,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. but where it is in truth, it is like it ſelfe, even like Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>Overcomming evill with good, in all meekneſſe, love, patience, long-ſuffering, being reviled,</hi> they <hi>revile</hi> not again, <hi>gentle towards all men,</hi> and by this means, and no otherwiſe, <hi>they heap coales of fire on the heads of thoſe that are</hi> enemies unto them, and ſo mightily ſtill and ſuccesfully, but ſo as by ſuffering they overcome.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> more then ſeems in his Epiſtle, to endeavour to get himſelfe a name, to be in his, as ſome in the ages paſt were in theirs, <hi>famous</hi> for oppoſing <hi>Schiſme, Hereſie,</hi> this might come to paſſe, if the time to come ſhould exceed the preſent time in <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> but the light that now ſhines manifeſts his folly very much, and that to very many already, how then will his <hi>works abide the fire?</hi> when <hi>the day ſhall reveale</hi> it to all; this therefore befalls M. <hi>Edwards</hi> in his Treatiſe, which accompanies all that <hi>doe things in the darke,</hi> he miſ-repreſents the truth, he <hi>ſtumbles</hi> at, which he muſt needs doe, becauſe he ſees it not in the <hi>light,</hi> in which alone <hi>it ſhines,</hi> in ſo much that that is now from M. <hi>Edwards</hi> mouth, miſtaken pen and judgement, <hi>undoubted blaſphemie,</hi> might be at the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:159660:19"/>firſt ſpeaking, everlaſting <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goſpel,</hi> Chriſts Doctrine, which was <hi>truth,</hi> flowing from the <hi>glorious fountain of it,</hi> was yet when repreſented by the Phariſees, ſuch as they took it to be, <hi>very falſe, vile, and abſurd,</hi> witneſſe the ſtories the <hi>Jews</hi> have of Chriſt and his Doctrine to this day, like the ſtories the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have of <hi>Luther,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſo that as the Phariſees did <hi>Chriſts;</hi> and as the Papiſts doe <hi>Luthers,</hi> ſo doth M. <hi>Edwards miſ-ſhape,</hi> and <hi>diſguiſe,</hi> the glorious truth and doctrine of ſome, <hi>into a lie,</hi> this time, the truths friend, will make appear, but I undertake not to juſtifie either Schiſme or Hereſie, there is too much of either found in the Land, and that even there, and amongſt them, that moſt cry out againſt it
<note n="i" place="margin">Which is true according to M. <hi>Edwards</hi> &amp; his friends owne maxime, the greateſt Cutpurſe crys Cutpurſe moſt, by the ſame rule, let all judge whether M. <hi>Edwards</hi> be not the greateſt Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick: I pray God it prove not true.</note>, occaſioned by the long time of darkneſſe we have been in, and now <hi>truth</hi> comes abroad, errour goes forth with it, and in a <hi>mantle</hi> like unto it, yet this I can be bold in, becauſe of <hi>this like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> truth receives more blame then that which indeed <hi>deſerves it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2 <hi>Particular.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> pretending more eminently then others to <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> hath in that Court of his (hearing onely the witneſſes of one ſide) paſt a threefold ſentence on me, and would have all men <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</hi> of the judgement he pronounceth, which is, that at <hi>Gloceſter</hi> I was firſt <hi>erroneous,</hi> then <hi>incorrigible,</hi> and for both caſt out of town. Here he thought to ſtrike at two at once, and one of them, one of the greateſt, and the moſt eminent in the Land, and that through the ſides of him, that is indeed one of the <hi>meaneſt</hi> of the ſervants of Chriſt and the Kingdoms, <hi>viz.</hi> my ſelfe, he ſecretly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braids, the ever <hi>honoured,</hi> and therefore <hi>moſt noble,</hi> becauſe the moſt <hi>conſtant Patriot</hi> of his Countrey, and <hi>lover</hi> of good men, my <hi>Lord Say,</hi> and that for reſpecting me (as Chriſt did the man caſt out by <hi>the Jews,</hi> for confeſſing him) when I had been ſo <hi>apparently</hi> wronged by others, it being the true character of thoſe that are both great and good, to reſpect the <hi>unjuſtly oppreſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Edwards</hi> might in conſcience have thought (who ever were his informers) on the Engliſh proverbe, <hi>one mans tale's good,</hi> till <hi>another's heard,</hi> or which is more to be <hi>beeded,</hi> that of the Wiſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:159660:20"/>man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.17. he <hi>He that is firſt in his own cauſe, ſeemeth juſt, but his neighbour commeth and ſearcheth him out,</hi> and makes it to appear otherwiſe, ſo the firſt goes away aſhamed: M. <hi>Edwards</hi> knowing I was in Town, and entertained by <hi>a great man</hi> (as hee confeſſeth) might have had recourſe to me for ſatisfaction, if not for <hi>mine,</hi> yet for that <hi>great mans ſake,</hi> and not ſo apparently to wound his own <hi>reputation,</hi> to wound others, in ſending abroad in <hi>print,</hi> a moſt notorious <hi>untruth,</hi> but he had a <hi>moneths minde</hi> to reproach my <hi>Lord Say,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wit. Mr. <hi>Cr.</hi>
                  </note> and that he knew not how to do <hi>immediately,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers having ſped ſo ill <hi>before him,</hi> for ſuch like <hi>unheard of boldneſſe,</hi> therefore he takes occaſion from me, when none was given by me, to doe it. Surely a <hi>good man</hi> would have done otherwiſe, been as carefull of anothers <hi>name</hi> and honour (eſpecially of one of the <hi>Peers</hi> and <hi>Pillars</hi> of the Land) as his own, but it ſeemes he thinks his <hi>tongue is his own,</hi> and therefore under <hi>no controul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> and they that will may <hi>know,</hi> that I was neither erroneous, or incorrigible, and therefore not caſt out of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> for either, I have printed this <hi>relation,</hi> wherein may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the whole truth of the matter (the conſciences of mine oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers <hi>being judge</hi>) that no errour could be (though it was induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſought after) picked out of any <hi>Sermon, diſcourſe,</hi> or <hi>Prayer,</hi> was heard from me, either in <hi>publike</hi> or <hi>private,</hi> and for this I chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge M. <hi>Edwards</hi> and all the World, if they can, to <hi>contradict:</hi> but herein it doth ſufficiently appear, becauſe they could not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten any errour that way upon me, they made tryall of me, though in a moſt <hi>un-due, un-chriſtiſtian,</hi> and <hi>un-brotherly</hi> way; by theſe ten Queſtions, with what meekneſſe and ſobriety, let the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of the ſecond <hi>Queſtion</hi> give all the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to judge, that they might be ſure they thought to <hi>catch me,</hi> they would caſt out their line <hi>far enough,</hi> which ſurely they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have done, it being ſo great a blemiſh to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but that they were <hi>confident</hi> to bring me into a <hi>ſnare:</hi> yet Gods wiſdom was ſuch, that after foure dayes ſolemne <hi>meeting,</hi> my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and converſation appeared far more <hi>innocent</hi> then before, and therefore at the concluſion of the laſt dayes <hi>ſolemne</hi> diſpute, I was pronounced free from the charge of errour laid againſt me,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:159660:20"/>and that by M. <hi>Brummidge,</hi> a learned gentleman of the <hi>Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee,</hi> who was as <hi>Moderator</hi> during the diſpute, which he did in the name of that whole <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and therefore M. <hi>Corbet</hi> ſpake aloud to this purpoſe, that though my words were juſtifiable, yet my <hi>meaning</hi> was otherwiſe, wherefore my <hi>meaning</hi> was indeed condemned in <hi>Gloceſter</hi> by M. <hi>Corbet,</hi> and perhaps by others, when my <hi>words</hi> and <hi>actions</hi> were found, and therefore declared <hi>blameleſſe,</hi> and that doth yet more fully appear, for though there was a double Order from the Committee for my removall, the copie of the firſt is before inſcribed, for the readers view, but the copie of the other I could by no means get, yet in neither of them was I <hi>charged</hi> with <hi>errour,</hi> neither was it rendred as a reaſon of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movall, the onely reaſon that I could finde in <hi>either,</hi> was to give <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to the importunity of ſome <hi>Miniſters,</hi> to whom my <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> or rather the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of Chriſt, was a <hi>burthen,</hi> and therefore M. <hi>Holford</hi> publikely deſired the City, to eaſe them of that <hi>burthen, by putting Chriſt out of Town</hi> (for that was the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion he uſed) to whom many were ready enough to ſubmit.</p>
               <p>As for my journy to <hi>Briſtol</hi> which (M. <hi>Edwards</hi> having <hi>ſpies from</hi> every Quarter, takes notice of) I need not make <hi>Apologie,</hi> thoſe that were his <hi>informers</hi> could have told him my exceeding <hi>loſſes there,</hi> to a greater <hi>value,</hi> then I know how to make up again, but our loſſes are <hi>nothing</hi> in theſe mens eyes; (therefore that I may uſe M. <hi>Calamies</hi> words, in his Apologie againſt M. <hi>Burton, pag.</hi> 8.) M. <hi>Edwards</hi> and his <hi>informer,</hi> ſitting as Lords over my <hi>conſcience,</hi> are not aſhamed to judge of my intentions, the reaſon of my jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney muſt needs be, to ſow Schiſme there, he might doubtleſſe with more <hi>love;</hi> have thought he is gon to <hi>recover,</hi> if it may be, ſome of the goods he was <hi>plundered of,</hi> as an eminent <hi>Miniſter of the City,</hi> ſpake with more <hi>moderation,</hi> when he ſaw me going forth of Town, beſides, all in and about <hi>Briſtol</hi> know, that I have been exerciſed in the publike Miniſtry of the Goſpel for many years in thoſe parts, and that through the <hi>grace of God,</hi> with a conſtant bleſſing <hi>from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,</hi> to the rejoycing of many <hi>in the Lord,</hi> thereabouts, and who themſelves are <hi>my joy</hi> and <hi>crown in the Lord,</hi> and therefore I am not aſhamed to declare my <hi>longing</hi> after them, to impart unto them
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:159660:21"/>ſome <hi>ſpirituall gift,</hi> that we might be mutually <hi>comforted</hi> by the <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>joy</hi> one of another, here again, therefore, I ſhall <hi>challenge</hi> M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> or his informer, <hi>who ever he be,</hi> to make it appear, if they can, that either my <hi>Doctrine, manner</hi> of life, <hi>purpoſe, faith,</hi> I have been theſe <hi>ten years</hi> converſant in, hath been any other then as becomes the Goſpel, either in <hi>Briſtol</hi> or elſewhere, which if they <hi>doe not,</hi> as I know they <hi>cannot,</hi> let all the world take <hi>notice,</hi> they abuſe their brother without <hi>a cauſe,</hi> and for this their ſlander, are in danger both of the judgment of God, and men, whom yet I deſire, both <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> (as my ſelfe <hi>do</hi>), to <hi>forgive.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Concluſion, by way of</hi> advice <hi>to Maſter</hi> Edwards, <hi>and thoſe of his</hi> Spirit, <hi>drawn from</hi> experience, <hi>but according to the</hi> Scripture: Rule, <hi>and</hi> Phraſe.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>TWo things ſeem to <hi>trouble</hi> you, and thoſe of your <hi>mina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> (for worſer things I will not preſume to <hi>divine</hi> of you) and you being troubled by <hi>them,</hi> you trouble others <hi>alſo,</hi> for they that are troubled <hi>themſelves,</hi> are uſually, if not always, a <hi>trouble</hi> in the places where they are to others, whether <hi>families, Cities, Kingdoms:</hi> And theſe are, 1 Diffidence in God. And 2 ſelfe confidence (the <hi>root</hi> from whence <hi>ſprings</hi> all our <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi>) Hence three things you ſeem perplexed with the fear of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of <hi>errour,</hi> becauſe of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> (to interpret the beſt of you and others of your minde.) 1 The Kingdoms <hi>Wealo:</hi> 2 The Churches <hi>peace:</hi> 3 Your <hi>own</hi> and <hi>others</hi> ſettlement: But for the firſt conſider, Is not Chriſt <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Nations?</hi> doth not he uphold the <hi>worlds</hi> by the <hi>word</hi> of his <hi>power?</hi> is not the Kingdom <hi>His,</hi> and at His <hi>diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall?</hi> he ſits at the <hi>ſterne,</hi> and <hi>guides</hi> it, who hath <hi>redeemed</hi> it with his <hi>bloud?</hi> Oh that <hi>you,</hi> and all the <hi>Kingdom</hi> could ſee <hi>him</hi> taking <hi>care</hi> of it, as <hi>hitherto</hi> he hath done. And for the Churches peace, is it not <hi>durable,</hi> like it ſelfe, and <hi>him</hi> that gives it? an <hi>everlaſting</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:159660:21"/>peace extended to it like a <hi>river,</hi> even the <hi>peace of God</hi> which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the <hi>underſtanding</hi> of either men or Angels, effectually to <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbe.</hi> Chriſt gives <hi>peace,</hi> not as the world <hi>giveth,</hi> to take it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>again,</hi> wherefore it is a true poſition, where men have not peace <hi>with God,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> with <hi>another,</hi> they are rather <hi>out</hi> of, then in the <hi>Church,</hi> for the <hi>Church</hi> is a Kingdom cannot be <hi>ſhaken:</hi> and for <hi>your ſelves,</hi> if <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> are you not upon a <hi>Rock?</hi> why then like <hi>Ahaz</hi> and his <hi>people</hi> are you <hi>moved,</hi> as the <hi>trees</hi> of the wood are <hi>mooved</hi> with the <hi>wind,</hi> and not rather are at <hi>reſt</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and in <hi>him,</hi> by <hi>faith,</hi> quiet <hi>from fear of evill,</hi> he that <hi>wavereth,</hi> is like a <hi>wave</hi> of the <hi>Sea,</hi> driven with the <hi>winde,</hi> and <hi>toſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Advice</hi> then is, have <hi>faith in God,</hi> for <hi>Kingdom, Church, your ſelves,</hi> he that <hi>beleeveth,</hi> ſhall not be <hi>aſhamed:</hi> A beleeving <hi>Kingdom,</hi> a beleeving <hi>Church,</hi> a beleeving <hi>man,</hi> ſhall not be <hi>moved,</hi> but diſtruſt the <hi>arme</hi> of <hi>fleſh,</hi> your <hi>wiſdom, zeal, government,</hi> you ſo <hi>contend</hi> about, the weapons of that warfare muſt not be <hi>carnall,</hi> that muſt take <hi>down</hi> thoſe ſtrong <hi>holds of Satan; Errour,</hi> and <hi>falſe worſhip,</hi> but ſuch as are <hi>mighty through God,</hi> thinke not as <hi>Uzzah</hi> did (of whom men ſpeak ſo much at this day, though without knowledge) that the <hi>Arke will fall,</hi> unleſſe you put to your hand (in an un-due manner) to <hi>ſupport</hi> it, and know you not tis true alone of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>government</hi> is upon his <hi>ſhoulders,</hi> he that <hi>puts to</hi> his hand as <hi>thinking</hi> he <hi>ſupports</hi> it, <hi>profanes</hi> it, &amp; diſhonours the High-prieſt that is <hi>entruſted</hi> with the care of it, more commit the ſin of <hi>Uzzah,</hi> then men at this day are aware of, the <hi>ſpiritualty</hi> (as <hi>they ſpeake,</hi> that would keep up the diſtinction ſtill) more then the <hi>temporalty,</hi> run upon this <hi>rock,</hi> and have done ſo of a <hi>long time,</hi> who have <hi>taken all</hi> into their <hi>own hands,</hi> if as Chriſt were not <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>inheritance</hi> not <hi>His,</hi> but <hi>theirs,</hi> and therefore have <hi>divided</hi> it, (as the <hi>Jews</hi> did) among <hi>themſelves:</hi> let us then <hi>remit</hi> the <hi>care</hi> of theſe things, ſo far as we are concerned in <hi>them</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that <hi>careth</hi> for us according to the Apoſtles rule, <hi>be carefull for
<note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 4 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> nothing,</hi> &amp;c. but will you neglect to doe what you can to preſerve the Kingdomes weale, the Churches peace, our owne, and others ſettlement in the truth? God forbid, provided yet, we obſerve theſe three cautions: 1 That we in the uſe of means, keep within our Spheare, as many doe not. 2 That what wee doe, we doe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:159660:22"/>in truth, for means uſed without faith, is like fire painted on the wall; it makes a blaze, but gives no heat. 3 That the remedy be proportioned to the diſtemper. For it doth appeare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſtrange and <hi>unchriſtian</hi> (that I ſay not <hi>Antichriſtian)</hi> and it will doe ſo more and more, that Errour, Schiſme, Hereſie, which is the <hi>Gangrene</hi> you pretend ſo excedingly to feare, (being in the very nature of it a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>ſoule</hi> diſtemper,) the temporall ſword (according to the Popiſh tenent) ſhould be thought the onely and the moſt <hi>effectuall</hi> means for the <hi>cure</hi> of, whether this be not to pretend onely to be a <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> a ſoule Phyſitian, and yet to have recourſe wholy to anothers box for ointment to do the <hi>cure:</hi> Hence it is that ſo many are proclaimed Schiſmaticks, Hereticks in the Pulpit, to provoke and engage the Magiſtrate, before there is any argument or Scripture ſufficient brought for the proving of them to be ſuch; even to this day, well nigh all hath been taken in for Oracle, that ſome few men (pretending <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>zeale,</hi> for <hi>holy Church</hi>) hath ſuggeſted to the Rulers of the earth, to the ſhedding of the <hi>bloud</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> and turning <hi>Kingdoms</hi> upſide down: But all <hi>praiſe</hi> be given to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> ſung to him that ſits on the Throne, this Book of <hi>deceit</hi> begins to be opened, and the Kingdoms learn of Chriſt to read it, that the <hi>Nations</hi> for this <hi>cauſe</hi> (we hope) may learn war no more.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> It is no Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox to affirm, that ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence is haunted with exceeding fear.</note> The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<list>
                     <item>Emblem,</item>
                     <item>Character,</item>
                  </list> Of an unbelieving, ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confident man is,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Magor miſſabib,</hi> Feare round about.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>He fears where no fear is,</hi> a <hi>&amp; fear</hi> hath <hi>torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Again,</p>
               <p>The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<list>
                     <item>Emblem,</item>
                     <item>Character,</item>
                  </list> Of him that hath <hi>Faith in God,</hi> is,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Noah</hi> in the <hi>Arke,</hi> or <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> in the <hi>clift</hi> of the <hi>rock:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>He is not afraid of any <hi>evill tydings,</hi> he fears nor the loſſe of <hi>life, eſtate,</hi> leaſt of all, the <hi>loſſe of his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> His heart is <hi>establiſhed</hi> with <hi>grace,</hi> and not with <hi>meats</hi> &amp; outward things.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>To the Reader, line 21. r. Apoſtles advice.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
